(86)18851830977 10084, Beijing, China **Aiwei Liu**

Ph.D. Student

Homepage: <u>exlaw.github.io</u> <u>github.com/exlaw</u>

liuaw20@mails.tsinghua.edu.cn

I am a fourth-year Ph.D student. My research interests lie in the fields of natural language processing and deep learning. In particular, I am interested in building more robust and secure natural language generation algorithms and focus on:

- The robustness of converting a database schema related question into a SQL query.
- Text watermarking for Large Language Models.
- Safety alignment of Large Language Models.

East Main Buildings, Tsinghua University

EDUCATION

Ph.D., School of Software, Tsinghua University, Advisor: Associate professor Lijie Wen

2020 — present

B.Eng., Software Institute, Nanjing University, GPA: 4.6/5.0, ranking: 5/220

2016 - 2020

PUBLICATIONS

Semantic Enhanced Text-to-SQL Parsing via Iteratively Learning Schema Linking Graph

Aiwei Liu, Xuming Hu, Li Lin, Lijie Wen

In Proceedings of the 28th ACM SIGKDD International Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining (SIGKDD), 2022

• Character-level White-Box Adversarial Attacks against Transformers via Attachable Subwords Substitution

Aiwei Liu, Honghai Yu, Xuming Hu, Shuang Li, Li Lin, Fukun Ma, Yawen Yang, Lijie Wen

In Proceedings of the 2022 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EM)

In Proceedings of the 2022 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP), 2022

Exploring the Compositional Generalization in Context Dependent Text-to-SQL Parsing

Aiwei Liu, Wei Liu, Xuming Hu, Shuang Li, Fukun Ma, Yawen Yang, Lijie Wen In The Findings of Association for Computational Linguistics (Findings of ACL), 2023

CHEF: A Pilot Chinese Dataset for Evidence-Based Fact-Checking

Xuming Hu, Zhijiang Guo, Guanyu Wu, Aiwei Liu, Lijie Wen, Phlip S.Yu

In The 2022 Conference of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics (NAACL), 2022

• GAUSSIAN PRIOR REINFORCEMENT LEARNING FOR NESTED NAMED ENTITY RECOGNITION

Yawen Yang, Xuming Hu, Fukun Ma, Shuang Li, **Aiwei Liu**, Lijie Wen, Phlip S.Yu

In 2023 IEEE International Conference on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing (ICASSP), 2023

• GDA: Generative Data Augmentation Techniques for Relation Extraction Tasks

Xuming Hu*, **Aiwei Liu***, Zeqi Tan, Xin Zhang, Chenwei Zhang, Irwin King, Philip S. Yu In The Findings of Association for Computational Linguistics (Findings of ACL), 2023

• Entity-to-Text based Data Augmentation for various Named Entity Recognition Tasks

Xuming Hu, Yong Jiang, **Aiwei Liu**, Zhongqiang Huang, Pengjun Xie, Fei Huang, Lijie Wen, Philip S. Yu In The Findings of Association for Computational Linguistics (Findings of ACL), 2023

• RAPL: A Relation-Aware Prototype Learning Approach for Few-Shot Document-Level Relation Extraction

Shiao Meng, Xuming Hu, **Aiwei Liu**, Shu'ang Li, Fukun Ma, Yawen Yang, Lijie Wen

In Proceedings of the 2022 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP), 2023

• AMR-based network for aspect-based sentiment analysis

Fukun Ma, Xuming Hu, Aiwei Liu, Yawen Yang, Philip S. Yu, Lijie Wen

In Proceedings of Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL), 2023

• A Multi-level Supervised Contrastive Learning Framework for Low-Resource Natural Language Inference

Shu'ang Li, Xuming Hu, Li Lin, Aiwei Liu, Lijie Wen, Philip S. Yu

IEEE/ACM Transactions on Audio, Speech, and Language Processing

•Reading Broadly to Open Your Mind Improving Open Relation Extraction With Search Documents Under Self-Supervisions

Xuming Hu, Zhaochen Hong, Chenwei Zhang, **Aiwei Liu**, Shiao Meng, Lijie Wen, Irwin King, Philip S. Yu IEEE Transactions on Knowledge and Data Engineering

• Enhancing Cross-lingual Natural Language Inference by Soft Prompting with Multilingual Verbalizer

Shuang Li, Xuming Hu, Aiwei Liu, Yawen Yang, Fukun Ma, Philip S. Yu, Lijie Wen

In The Findings of Association for Computational Linguistics (Findings of ACL), 2023

(86)18851830977 10084, Beijing, China **Aiwei Liu**

Ph.D. Student

Homepage: <u>exlaw.github.io</u> <u>github.com/exlaw</u>

East Main Buildings, Tsinghua University

FILD. Studettt

liuaw20@mails.tsinghua.edu.cn

PREPRINTS

• A Survey of Text Watermarking in the Era of Large Language Models

Aiwei Liu*, Leyi Pan*, Yijian Lu, Jingjing Li, Xuming Hu, Lijie Wen, Irwin King, Philip S. Yu

• An Unforgeable Publicly Verifiable Watermark for Large Language Models

Aiwei Liu, Leyi Pan, Xuming Hu, Shu'ang Li, Lijie Wen, Irwin King, Philip S. Yu Submitted to International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR) 2024

• A Semantic invariant Robust Watermark for Large Language Models

Aiwei Liu, Leyi Pan, Xuming Hu, Shiao Meng, Lijie Wen

Submitted to International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR) 2024

WORK EXPERIENCE

Apple AIML Group Mar. 2023 - present

Research Intern, Advisor: Dr. Meng Cao and Dr. Xiang Kong

Online collab with California, United States

Project: Prompt Difficulty Evaluation, Unsupervised safety alignment for LLM

- Keywords: Large Language Model, Safety Alignment
- Accomplishments: 1) Developed a LLM-based automatic attributes identification methods for prompt difficulty evaluation.
- 2) Designed a safety alignment method for LLM that does not require manual or GPT-4 annotation of preference data.

Chinese University of Hong Kong

Nov. 2023 - present

Visiting Scholar, Advisor: Prof Irwin King (IEEE Fellow)

Hongkong, China

Project: Watermark for Large Language Models

- Keywords: Large Language Model, Safety Alignment
- Accomplishments: 1) Developed an unforgeable publicly verifiable watermark for Large Language Models 2) Write a
 comprehensive survey about the text watermarking in the era of LLMs.

SELECTED HONORS AND AWARDS

| Tsinghua Excellent Student Award (SecondClass) | | |
|---|---|------------------------|
| Outstanding Graduates Nanjing University China Electronics Technology Group Scholarship National Scholarship Hainan Airlines Scholarship | 2022 2020 2019 | |
| | | 2018 |
| | | COMPETITION EXPERIENCE |
| | Al Application Innovation Competition of BAAI | |
| Excellence Award: Atvideo Text-to-Video tool | 2021 | |
| Vivo and Nanjing University Hackathon | 2019 | |
| First Prize: ChainPaper Blockchain-based Paper Sharing Platform | | |
| | | |

PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES

Program Committee/ Reviewer

- The Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL)
- The Annual Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP)
- The Annual Conference of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics (NAACL)
- The Annual Conference of the European Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics (EACL)
- The ACM WWW International World Wide Web Conference (WWW)

PERSONAL LIFE

刘瑷玮 is my name in Chinese characters. I was born and grown in Rizhao, China until I went to college in Nanjing, China.Basketball has always been my passion, and I have been a valuable member of my college basketball team, consistently leading as the top scorer in multiple seasons. Additionally, I also have a great interest in cycling and swimming.